We're finally back!
The air up here is so much better than the dungeons.
Is this sunrise or sunset?
Do not touch the window. The spell is still in effect here.
Kabro, I'm reporting to the Island Lord tomorrow.
I'd like you to join me as a witness.
Do you plan on telling him about everything?
I don't think it's necessary to mention Laios and his party.
Mostly, I just don't want Fallon to murder anyone else.
That makes sense.
Why don't you use the rest of the day to get some sleep?
Oh! See that, Kuro?
Big ship. It's huge.
I wonder if the people on it have lots of money!
This isn't good.
Toshiro, we need to see the Island Lord right away.
Is that ship special?
It belongs to the Elves of the West.
That bird figurehead.
Must be the Canaries, then.
They appear when dungeons reach a certain level of danger.
When that happens, their mission is to investigate the dungeon and conquer it.
I've heard rumors that they've been putting pressure on the Island Lord.
But it looks like they're switching to coercion.
How is something like that allowed?
Isn't this a Tall Man region?
To the Elves and Dwarves, races with short lives are like infants.
And sadly, the Island Lord is not very good at negotiating.
Let's hurry.
Huh?
Hey!
If it isn't Shuro!
Hello, Nomari.
Where's Fallon?
Laios and the others haven't given up yet, though.
That's so.
They still eating monsters?
Yes, they are.
Excuse me, but we're here to see the Island Lord.
Oh, you're out of luck, then.
Some important people suddenly came to talk with him.
And they've been in there for hours now.
So we're too late.
We have to go inside.
Is that really wise?
If the Elves take control of the dungeon, it's over.
The town I'm from also prospered from a dungeon.
One day, monsters flooded the town.
The Elves came and many died.
Why was my family part of the ones who were killed?
My mother was a single parent and did everything she could to raise me.
She didn't deserve to die like that.
I vowed to never let that happen again.
The system in which a single race holds all the power,
it isn't healthy for anyone.
Forgive me, but I've come here to deliver a report to the Island Lord.
Excuse me?
As you can see, we're in the middle of something.
Come back later.
It's a report about the situation in the dungeon.
Please, hear me out.
Seriously?
Stand your ground.
Make it brief.
Not too long ago, during our exploration,
we encountered a human who turned into a monster.
What?
Damn it.
A chimera.
It's progressing faster than expected.
See?
I told you all!
We didn't have time to twiddle our thumbs and wait for an answer!
Let's give the order to make landfall.
We won't allow that!
The elderly need not get worked up.
Country borders are so trivial compared to the lives of people.
Just who do you think you are, treating me like I'm old and senile?
Tonsu, please.
I think we've said enough.
What the?
You're a true island lord, understanding and wise.
Now, if you would please stamp here.
Don't do it!
You can't give in!
Did we actually end up making things worse here?
The truth is...
If I had enough strength to conquer a dungeon,
there wouldn't be a problem.
But I don't.
So I started looking around for adventurers who were more skilled that I could assist.
However, most of the people I found were self-serving and worthless.
By the time I accepted my fate and tried to conquer the dungeon myself,
I heard rumors about the Toten siblings.
I have a feeling that they were brought up pretty well.
They have good instincts, but no real ambition.
They're honestly kind of weird.
The more I found out, the stranger they seemed.
Despite not being that strong, they reached the deeper floors of the dungeon.
They would give money to people with poor reputations,
and their origins in the strange company they kept were hard to follow.
Still, there's something about the brother that made me feel
he was deeply connected to the destiny of this island.
The question was, would his role be good or bad?
To decide that, I wanted to speak with him directly.
And once I did, I finally understood.
He only thinks about monsters.
Therefore, we can't trust him to consider the future of the island.
But there's one thing I can say for sure.
At this moment, among the Tall Men, he's the one who's closest to the heart of the dungeon.
This will more than likely be the first and last chance we get,
so I can't let the elves get in his way.
I'll figure out what to do about him after.
Enough already.
You can do whatever you want.
My lord!
I'll let them know to make landfall.
Please, wait!
Huh?
It's too dangerous.
The types of monsters, architecture, and environments.
All of it's in turmoil.
We're already aware of this.
It's a characteristic of dungeons showing growth.
We have to stop it as soon as possible.
In human terms, a growth spurt.
This is when it requires the most nutrients.
What's all this now?
About 15 years ago,
a dungeon destroyed my hometown.
It was a town called Utaya.
15 years ago?
Then what did that mean?
No way!
Are you the child they see survived that incident?
I did hear that the vice captain or someone had brought a young one home with them.
Yes.
They took care of me for several years.
Oh?
You were probably spoiled, but became an adventurer.
It was my dream to join a squad, but I couldn't as a tall man.
I didn't want to repeat that tragedy,
so I wanted a way to help.
How admirable.
Are you getting enough to eat?
You should go and visit the vice captain sometime!
Anyway,
you mentioned nutrients.
Tell me more.
Well, because of your efforts,
Utaya's dungeon was quickly destroyed.
However,
there were many casualties among the soldiers and civilians.
It was due to the dead turning into monsters and eating the living.
Soldiers were ambushed before they could do anything.
Rely on numbers and Utaya will repeat itself.
I suggest we seal the dungeon instead.
We can't do anything that will end up feeding it.
I'm pretty sure it's not your intention to cause damage to the dungeon during combat anyway.
How many people are inside?
The majority of them are on the first floor.
Let's evacuate them slowly.
All humans have some sort of connection.
And I know some people who can definitely help out.
So just leave it to me!
Cabro,
he still ate monsters despite everything he went through?
Begin preparations
for the investigation.
Huh?
I suspect you're plotting something.
If that's the case,
show me what you've got.
Should anything go wrong,
my troops will rush in.
Understood.
Yes.
So are they like scrambled eggs?
Huh?
You said before that people compare souls to eggs.
But if you're referring to souls that are mixed together,
then what would that mean in relation to how eggs are cooked?
For example,
scrambled eggs,
a sunny-side-up egg,
and a poached egg
would all have different stories.
Listen, Senshi.
I didn't make that comparison
for you to take what I said
and try to make a joke out of it.
Who's making jokes?
I was actually impressed
by how interesting a comparison it was.
There's nothing else that behaves
in as many different ways as an egg does.
For example,
eggs get firm when heated,
but the white and yolk solidify
at different temperatures.
Frothiness,
moisture retention,
viscosity,
and the most interesting one,
emulsification.
Even things that don't mix naturally
like oil and water
mixed beautifully
under the right conditions.
Just like this.
Well, that's...
Wait, souls are actually nothing like eggs.
Laios,
you mind handing me that bread there?
It's ready.
So, how are we supposed to eat this?
Pick up the bread with your knife and fork,
then use the bread to scoop the yolk and sauce
as you eat.
Delicious as usual.
If you don't mind,
could you stop looking around at stuff
that isn't really there?
Or is there something?
I don't think so.
I just thought I felt some kind of presence.
Huh?
Does that mean this isn't a hallucination?
Well, when I'd gotten mana sickness,
remember when I mentioned
I was seeing and hearing things?
That never went away.
Seriously?
Why didn't you say something?
Because Chill would just yell at me
and tell me I'm sick in the head.
That's because you are.
What are you hallucinating?
Day in and day out,
something keeps trying to talk to me.
At first, I couldn't tell what it was saying.
But gradually,
its voice and shape started getting clearer.
It's pretty scary,
so I've been pretending not to see it.
Then you could actually hear me speaking after all.
So what did it say?
Well, it's not too happy that I was ignoring it.
I wonder if talking to it is okay.
Do you think it's evil?
Uh, not sure.
Possibly.
Hello there!
Can I help you with something?
Uh-huh.
What's it saying now?
It's mad at me because I thought it was an evil ghost.
Also,
it's asking if we've forgotten
that it saved us from the, uh, mage.
Huh?
Oh, wait!
I remember!
Right.
How could I forget that whole thing?
Please give it our thanks.
Hmm.
Mm-hmm.
I guess it wants to introduce us to someone?
Thoughts?
It's not the god of death, is it?
Well,
we don't have many options, so...
All right.
We're ready to go whenever you are.
Oh!
What?
Wait.
What the heck?
Where are we?
Hey!
Out of the road, please!
Is that a unicorn?
That clothing.
Did you guys come from the outside?
No.
We came from the dungeon and...
I can't believe it.
Come with me.
I've never seen monsters be this docile before.
It's because they're ordered not to hurt us,
so we can coexist here.
Whoa.
That's not going to be the case for outsiders, though.
So make sure you hold on to the stuff I gave you.
Izutsumi?
Something wrong?
Teleportation sickness?
She's probably tired.
Is that the Golden Castle?
Sure is.
And the ghosts that brought us to this place,
are they actual residents, too?
Pretty much.
Well,
the person you're about to meet has more info.
Maybe they'll know why you were chosen,
because we sure don't.
We were chosen?
This is it.
Just sit tight, okay?
If you're looking for the master,
he went to the church.
It's them.
Huh?
Those guys?
Guess we came here at a pretty bad time.
Until the master comes back here,
why don't you try to relax in the village?
Seems like everyone really wants to show you
their hospitality.
What should we take them around to see first?
The village isn't that special, so...
They're all residents of the Golden Castle?
Yeah, but I don't see any old folk.
Honestly, I'd like to see
where the monsters are being raised.
Huh?
I want to take a tour of the fields
we saw on the way over.
Huh?
That's what you're interested in?
I mean, that's easy enough.
Hooray!
I'll just wait for them to get back.
Can't leave he's a tsumi alone anyway.
I agree.
That's a minotaur!
And it's female!
We milk this instead of cows.
Why are you raising monsters?
Oh, because normal livestock
was hard to get a hold of.
Oh!
What a beautiful field.
It's so well tended to.
Is everything here used up by the villagers?
We admittedly waste quite a lot of it.
But if we didn't have fields to keep us busy,
we'd have nothing to do.
It's mostly an appearance,
but we try to mimic surface life.
Really?
Isutsumi, are you okay?
At least she doesn't seem sick, I guess.
Sorry!
We don't mean to interrupt, but...
Dresses?
Exactly!
They're dresses we made by hand.
We've gotten so bored of modeling them ourselves.
We need the fresh face of an outsider to do it.
Sure, if you want me to.
Which should we try?
It has to be the red one!
You'll have to forgive us.
Our dresses might seem a little old-fashioned
from your perspective.
I'm sure it's fine.
Somehow this is different than what I expected.
Guess this is what happens
when you've been isolated for a thousand years.
Try this on next!
This is great!
I'm pretty picky about my alcohol,
but this isn't bad at all.
Happy to hear.
I've been serving it to my Orc customers,
and this recent batch is really popular among them.
Yeah, I bet.
Oh, what about wine?
Do you make that?
Well, I do,
but it's much newer than making ale.
Been doing that 400 years now,
so making the switch has been tricky.
That long, huh?
Sounds pretty established.
What generation are you?
I started it when I was 600,
so first generation.
Come again?
Chilchuk, guess what?
They let me milk a minotaur!
Hey, good for you.
Keep that to yourself next time.
This place is incredible!
They've completely succeeded in cultivating monsters
and made it an art!
Do you see that?
It's the biggest dryad garden I've ever seen!
The minotaur had four nipples like a cow!
I'm not feeling so good.
That was a once-in-a-lifetime experience.
You really missed out?
By the way,
where did the other two go?
What's with the weird non-sequitur?
Uh, we're over here.
What in the hell are you wearing?
Playing dress-up, huh?
Don't misunderstand!
I was asked to wear this, I swear!
I actually, this was the tamest one I tried on.
Marcelle, you, uh...
Uh, yeah?
Lyos?
You have any clue why she's stuck to you like that?
Oh, that, right!
Yeah, I have no idea!
That's so weird!
Uh, it's like she switched brains with a child or something!
Uh!
Oh!
Yeah!
Lots of barriers have been cast here in many different layers.
And it seems like it's affecting Izutsumi in some way.
It's because she's half-monster, right?
Yeah.
But I've never seen a barrier make monsters non-aggressive before.
I really wish I could decipher this.
But I don't know most of these characters,
and I don't have time to learn!
Why the hell do these things have to be so hard to read and secretive?
Anyway, this really is an amazing place.
Under different circumstances,
I wouldn't mind staying here forever.
Same here.
My apologies for the long wait.
It isn't much,
but we've prepared a warm meal for all of you.
This way, please.
Ah, welcome, everyone.
I've been wanting to meet you.
I'm Yod.
It's a pleasure.
You already know of Delgol, yes?
Well, he's my grandfather.
Delgol?
Please, feel free to take a seat.
You're wondering why I've called you here.
This will take some time to explain.
Let's see it first.
Uh, is this meat?
Yes!
As your party had specifically requested,
we prepared Minotaur meat!
Does everyone in the village routinely eat monsters, too?
There are some who do,
although we don't really need to consume food.
Huh?
Our sense of taste has completely dulled.
Aside from that,
we have no real appetite to speak of.
Such is the curse of immortality
that the mad mage cast on the people of this village.
Do you know why the mage would do something like that?
No.
When I grew old enough to know what was happening,
the mage was already in a state
where communicating with him was difficult.
But please, don't let our problems stop you.
Go eat up to your heart's content.
We may not get hungry,
but simply being able to watch others eat
still brings us joy.
Well, now, I definitely can't say
that I don't really want to eat this.
Grandfather.
For as long as I can remember,
he always blamed himself
for being the one who made the mad mage
become obsessed with black magic.
So in order to look for help,
he headed to the surface.
Perhaps you know.
How did he fare up there?
Well, from what I've heard,
he was seen emerging from the underground cemetery.
He claimed he was the king of a ruined country
and would give his entire kingdom
to the one who defeated the mad mage,
then turn to dust.
Is that so?
He's finally been released from his agony.
Knowing this brings me solace.
Many people have attempted to escape the curse
by leaving the village.
However, none have succeeded
and their physical bodies are lost as a result.
Without a body, you gradually lose yourself,
become an evil ghost,
and then are unable to return here.
I'm sure you've encountered these ghosts before.
Yeah.
We attacked them with holy water
and then made us for a bay out of them.
So, anyway,
you never told us why we were called to this place.
The prophecy.
Prophecy?
Indeed.
One shall arrive at the village
with winged sword in hand.
They will be the hero
who will defeat the mad mage
and set us all free.
Winged sword.
Does he mean Kensuke?
Well, there are wings on it, although...
Wait!
This lion face wasn't on here before!
When did...
The winged lion is our guardian deity.
He was imprisoned at the very bottom of the dungeon
by the mad mage.
However,
the lion still guides us
by telling us prophecies
by way of our dreams.
And those prophecies are why
my grandfather left for the surface.
Sir Laios,
there is more to the prophecy.
With the winged sword in their hand,
the hero will defeat the mad mage
and thus rise as the country's new king.
Wait!
You can't be serious!
He just picked up that sword by complete accident!
It was no accident.
The fact the sword is in this room with us
means it was something preordained.
Now, Sir Laios,
can you please promise me something?
Promise me you'll defeat the mad mage
and free everyone in this village!
But I...
Can you please let me think about it?
You gotta turn him down.
Why bother giving them hope like that?
Because I can't flat-out refuse.
Kensuke,
when'd you even get like this?
Huh, buddy?
Maybe it was when you got eaten
by the dungeon cleaners.
I was actually so nervous during all that,
I couldn't really taste any of the food
they made for us.
You've got some nerve, you know that?
Specifically requested by the party, huh?
It really didn't have that much flavor
to begin with.
Huh?
You said they have no appetite,
so they don't need to eat anything.
I think it's safe to assume
that's why they're not very good at cooking.
I just realized something.
The people in this village,
they don't really need to tend fields
and use dishware,
so why bother keeping them around?
What was the point in wasting all that energy
to continue maintaining them
for the last thousand years or so?
I reckon it's because they actually do need those things.
It helps them keep their sanity
and gives them a reason to live.
Laios,
when we were with the Orc Chief on the third floor,
I still remember exactly what you told them.
What did I say again?
Well,
make sure you take the night to think about it.
Do you mind if I sleep in here, too?
Go sleep in the room they gave you.
But I don't want to be alone in there.
And Izutsumi's being weird.
Come on, scoot over.
Just sleep on the floor.
His hands were so cold.
I don't want to be alone in there.